Draper Corporation Photographs 6612 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series B:1956-1989, black and white photograph (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Item 1977: Draper Company duplexes, Jones Road, 1916; black and white photograph (Box 10, Folder 5)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B1977. August 2, 1916. Image depicts Jones Road in Hopedale, Massachusetts, part of the Draper Company's "planned community." Duplexes line the street; a horse and wagon stands on the street; three small children play on the sidewalk; and a woman walks down the sidewalk on the left-hand side. Written on the reverse: "Tenements Aug. 2, 1916" but tenements in this context means housing for Draper Company employees. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 1978: Maple Street and Jones Road, 1916; black and white photograph (Box 10, Folder 5)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B1978. August 8, 1916. Image depicts the corner of Maple Street and Jones Road in Hopedale, Massachusetts, part of the Draper Company's "planned community." Compare this to Box 9, Folder 3, Item 1665, which was taken two years before when the road was being graded. Now a streetlight pole has been placed on the corner; trees have been planted; bushes and flowers are visible in front of the houses. Written on the reverse: "Tenements Aug. 8, 1916" but tenements in this context simply means housing for Draper Company employees. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series B:1990-2026: box no. 110-111, black and white photograph (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Item 2018: Lake Street from Draper Company Carpenter Shop, 1916; black and white photograph (Box 10, Folder 6)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2018. November 10, 1916. Image depicts houses on Lake Street in Hopedale, Massachusetts; photo taken from the elevation of the carpenter shop of the Draper Company. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. Original photograph by the Draper Company. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 2020: Draper Company Hose House and Andrews House from top of shop, 1916; black and white photograph (Box 10, Folder 6)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2020. November 10, 1916. Image depicts houses in Hopedale, Massachusetts; photo taken from the elevation of what is probably the carpenter shop of the Draper Company. This angle most likely represents the opposite angle seen in Item 2018, in this folder, also taken from the carpenter shop on the same date. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. Original photograph by the Draper Company. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series B:2027-2063: box no. 112-113, black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series B:2064-2099: box no. 114-115, black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series B:2100-2133: box no. 116-117, black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series B:2134-2167: box no. 118-119, black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series B:2168-2201: box no. 120-121, black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series B:2202-2233: box no. 122-123, black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Item 2202: Whitin-Owen feeler motion, Draper Corporation, black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2202. 1918-1919. Image depicts a close-up view of the Whitin-Owen feeler motion attached to a (presumably) Draper Corporation loom. A feeler is a device on a loom designed to transfer a full bobbin to the shuttle before the old one is entirely emptied. The feeler projects into the shuttle from the side and feels the yarn on the bobbin. When the bobbin is approaching emptiness, the feeler actuates the transfer motion and replaces the bobbin. The Whitin-Owen feeler motion was manufactured by the Whitin Machine Works of Whitinsville, Massachusetts The Draper Corporation manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 20.25 x 25.25 cm.
  - Item 2204: James Northrup, inventor of the Northrup Loom, 1918; black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2204. December 10, 1918. Image depicts a portrait of James Northrup (1856-1940), inventor of the Northrup Loom. He is pictured sporting a moustache and is dressed in suit and tie. The Draper Corporation produced the Northrup Loom, named for its inventor, who had emigrated from Keighley, Yorkshire, England in 1881. Northrup invented the first fully automatic loom, its basic feature being the filling-changing battery. Northrup looms were first marketed by Draper in 1894. Nothrup retired to California at the age of 42; as he appears to be in his late fifties or early sixties in this portrait, it is most likely a photograph of another photograph. 20.25 x 25.25 cm.
  - Item 2227: Draper Model D Loom, Atlantic Mill, 1919; black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2227. July 11, 1919. Photograph of a photograph. Image depicts a Draper Company (or Draper Corporation) Model D loom, which was a heavy standard loom. Loom is displayed against a white background; the original photo may have been done for advertising purposes. The "Atlantic Mill" referred to on the reverse of the print is probably the Atlantic Cotton Mills in Lawrence, Massachusetts, which were cotton mills. The Atlantic Mills were idle by 1913 and dismantled in March 1915. This loom may be been used in or at least sold to the Atlantic Cotton Mills by Draper, which was located in Hopedale, Massachusetts 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 2228: Draper Model R Loom, Mount Vernon-Woodberry, 1919; black and white photograph (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2228. April 1, 1919. Photograph of a photograph. Image depicts a Draper Corporation Model R loom, which is displayed against a white background; the original photo may have been done for advertising purposes. By 1919, Mount Vernon-Woodberry Mills Inc. operated a number of mills in Baltimore, Md., plus mills in some southern states; among other products some mills produced cotton duck. This loom may be been used in or at least sold to the Mount Vernon-Woodberry Mills by the Draper Corporation of Hopedale, Massachusetts 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series B:2234-2268: box no. 124-125, black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Item 2246: Sliding feeler for cops, Draper Corporation, 1919; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 1)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2246. July 1, 1919. Image depicts a close-up of a sliding feeler for cops. A feeler is a device on a loom designed to transfer a full bobbin to the shuttle before the old one is entirely emptied. The feeler projects into the shuttle from the side and feels the yarn on the bobbin. When the bobbin is approaching emptiness, the feeler actuates the transfer motion and replaces the bobbin. A cop is a yarn package. The Draper Corporation manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 2259: Field Day, general view, 1919; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 1)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2259. August 9, 1919. Image depicts groups of men, women, and children gathering at the baseball field for the event, most likely arranged by the Draper Corporation. Everyone is dressed in "Sunday best" and a few children in the right foreground are carrying balloons. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 2260: Field Day 1919, start of one-mile race, black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 1)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2260. August [9], 1919. Image depicts groups of men, women, and children gathering at the baseball field for the event, most likely arranged by the Draper Corporation. Everyone is dressed in "Sunday best." Four male runners have begun the race, starting in the left center background (shallow left field). Since the field is encircled with poles and rope, the runners apparently run a circuit around the field for a mile. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 2261: Officers of the Day, Draper Corporation, 1919; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 1)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2261. August 9, 1919. Image depicts a group of 36 men posed in an outside setting. Some are dressed in police (?) uniforms, some in suits and ties, and some in white shirts and ties. Each is wearing a ribbon or medal, signifying receipt of an honor or award. The ribbons read in part "Hopedale Annual Field Day Draper Corporation." The Draper Corporation hosted annual Field Days for its employees every August. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 2266: Adin Ballou House, 1919; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 1)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2266. September 1919. Image depicts the Adin Ballou House on Dutcher Street in Hopedale, Massachusetts The house is a two-story wooden house with two chimneys, and both front and back doors. A wrap-around porch and set of steps join the front entry with a walkway to the sidewalk and street. Shrubs and climbing vines surround the porch and house. Ballou (1803-1890) was a prominent proponent of pacifism, socialism and abolitionism, and the founder (in 1842) of the Hopedale Community, a utopian community blending a factory town with a religious-based commune. George and Ebenezer Draper withdrew their 75% of the community stock in 1856 to establish the Hopedale Manufacturing Company. Ballou continued on as Universalist pastor until retirement in 1880. The house was moved from its original location in 1900 to Dutcher Street and the porch added to the building. See Box 2, Folder 3, Item 188 and Item 199 for views of the house in its original location at Peace and Hopedale streets. Original photograph by the Draper Corporation. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 2267: Dr. Osborn House, Dutcher Street, 1919; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 1)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2267. September 1919. Image depicts a two-story wood-shingled house plus attic. Shutters are at each window and a wrap-around porch and set of steps join the front entry with a walkway to the sidewalk and street. Shrubs and climbing vines surround the porch and house. No information could be found about who Dr. Osborn (or Osborne) was. Original photograph by the Draper Corporation. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 2268: Draper Corporation tenements, Dutcher & Northrop streets, 1919; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 1)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2268. September 1919. Image depicts a two-story wood-shingled house with front porch and steps to front door. Corner view shows side of house with a set of back steps leading to a grassy yard. Other homes are in the background. These houses were built for Draper Corporation employees. Tenements in this context simply means employee housing and not the "slum" housing usually thought of in reference to the word tenements. Draper Company founders, brothers George and Ebenezer, believed that good houses made good workers and created a model self- contained company town with one of the best collections of architecturally significant double houses in the country. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series B:2269-2312: box no. 126-128, black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Item 2269: Park Street School, 1919; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2269. September 1919. Image depicts the Park Street School, a three-story brick building (the lower story is partially underground), with a cupola and three gable windows in the attic. The school was built on Park Street in 1914. A flagpole stands to the side of the school. Original photograph by the Draper Corporation. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 2270: Charles Austin House, Dutcher Street, 1919; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2270. September 1919. Image depicts a two-story wood-shingled house plus attic, located at 106 Dutcher Street in Hopedale, Massachusetts Shutters are at each window and a wrap-around porch and set of steps join the front entry with a walkway to the sidewalk and street. Only the center entrance of the porch is roofed however; the rest of the porch is open to show bay windows on either side of the front door. Shrubs surround the porch and house. The house was built by the Draper Company (or Draper Corporation), for its employee. Charles Austin was Draper's housing superintendent and supplemented his income by selling tires from his home. Original photograph by the Draper Corporation. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 2271: Draper Corporation tenements, Dutcher Street, 1919; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2271. September 1919. Image depicts a two-story wood-shingled house with attic. The house features a pitched roof and four bay windows on the front. Two entryways are connected by walkways to the sidewalk and street, indicating this was a two-family building. Shrubs and plants surround the house. A set of back steps is in view on one side of the house. This house was built for Draper Corporation employees. Tenements in this context simply means employee housing and not the "slum" housing usually thought of in reference to the word tenements. Draper Company founders, brothers George and Ebenezer, believed that good houses made good workers and created a model self-contained company town with one of the best collections of architecturally significant double houses in the country. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 2272: Draper Corporation tenements, 6 Peace Street, 1919; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2272. September 1919. Image depicts a two-story wood clapboard house with attic. Decorative framework outlines each gable. The house has four entry doors at front, indicating multiple families were in residence. The entryways are connected by walkways to the sidewalk and street. Shutters are at each window and climbing vines surround the entryways. A hydrangea bush and climbing rose on trellis enhance the grounds. This house was built for Draper Corporation employees. Tenements in this context simply means employee housing and not the "slum" housing usually thought of in reference to the word tenements. Draper Company founders, brothers George and Ebenezer, believed that good houses made good workers and created a model self-contained company town with one of the best collections of architecturally significant double houses in the country. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 2273: Draper Corporation tenements, 6 Lake Street, 1919; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2273. September 1919. Image depicts a two-story wood-shingled house with attic. The house has two arched entryways with recessed doors at the front. The entryways are connected by walkways to the sidewalk and street. Shutters are at each window and two bay windows are on the first floor. The house is flanked by two tall trees and other shrubs grow along the foundation. This house was built for Draper Corporation employees. Tenements in this context simply means employee housing and not the "slum" housing usually thought of in reference to the word tenements. Draper Company founders, brothers George and Ebenezer, believed that good houses made good workers and created a model self-contained company town with one of the best collections of architecturally significant double houses in the country. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 2274: Draper Corporation tenements, 86 Dutcher Street, 1919; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2274. September 1919. Image depicts a two-story wood-shingled house with attic. The house has two small open porches with recessed doors at the front. The entryways are connected by walkways to the sidewalk and tree-lined street (all the trees have wire netting around them for a distance of about four feet off the ground). Shutters are at each window. A set of back steps is in view at one side of the house and another house is partially in view on the other side. This house was built for Draper Corporation employees. Tenements in this context simply means employee housing and not the "slum" housing usually thought of in reference to the word tenements. Draper Company founders, brothers George and Ebenezer, believed that good houses made good workers and created a model self-contained company town with one of the best collections of architecturally significant double houses in the country. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 2275: Draper Corporation tenements, Jones Road and Dutcher Street, 1919; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2275. September 1919. Image depicts a two-story wood-shingled house with attic. The house appears to be photographed from the side, and features a large porch on the first floor. The entryway seems to be on the opposite side. Two bay windows are on the front side second floor level. Shutters are at each window. Trees and shrubs enhance the grounds. Tenements in this context simply means employee housing and not the "slum" housing usually thought of in reference to the word tenements. Draper Company founders, brothers George and Ebenezer, believed that good houses made good workers and created a model self-contained company town with one of the best collections of architecturally significant double houses in the country. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 2276: Draper Corporation tenements, Dutcher Street, 1919; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2276. September 1919. Image depicts a two-story wood-shingled house with two large gables on either end forming an attic. Some windows are diamond paned and all have shutters. The building is designed for occupancy by two families and has a double set of stairs at the front entrance. Shrubs and climbing vines surround the entry and house. Two small children play on the bottom step and another girl or young woman is barely visible at the far left. This house was built by the Draper Corporation for its employees. Tenements in this context simply means employee housing and not the "slum" housing usually thought of in reference to the word tenements. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 2277: Back yards, Lake Street, 1919; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2277. September 1919. Image depicts three houses--one on the left, one in the center background, and one on the right--partially hidden by multiple trees and bushes. An unpaved road leads straight back, while branching off to the left and right. These back yards appear to form a cul-de-sac. The houses in view were most likely housing built for Draper Corporation employees. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 2278: Draper Corporation tenements, 37 Progress Street, 1919; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2278. September 1919. Image depicts a two-story wood-shingled house with two chimneys. Most of the windows have shutters. The building is designed for occupancy by two families; there is a double set of steps in the front and a side porch can be glimpsed on the left. A walkway on the right most likely leads to another side porch. Shrubs and climbing vines surround the entry and house. This house was built by the Draper Corporation for its employees. Tenements in this context simply means employee housing and not the "slum" housing usually thought of in reference to the word tenements. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 2279: Draper Corporation Tenements, corner Dutcher & Freedom streets, 1919; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2279. September 1919. Image depicts a two-story wood clapboard house. Shutters are at each window and a set of steps leads to a porch with two separate entryways, indicating this was a duplex. A walkway connects the sidewalk and street with the house. Climbing vines surround the porch and some shrubs can be seen against the side of the house. A second house is partially seen in the back. This house was built by the Draper Corporation for its employees. Tenements in this context simply means employee housing and not the "slum" housing usually thought of in reference to the word tenements. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 2280: Draper Corporation tenements, corner Oak and Northrup streets, 1919; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2280. September 1919. Image depicts a two-story wood-shingled house with attic and two chimneys, and features some Tudor-type timbering as decoration on the attic level and the front porches. Windows have shutters. The building is designed for occupancy by two families; there are two separate front entrances and the one on the right has been screened in. Shrubs surround the entry and house; flowers have been planted around the two trees on the front lawn. Both streets have sidewalks but the streets appear unpaved. This house was built by the Draper Corporation for its employees. Tenements in this context simply means employee housing and not the "slum" housing usually thought of in reference to the word tenements. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 2283: Draper Corporation tenement, 24 Northrup Street, 1919; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2283. September 1919. Image depicts a two-story wood-shingled house. Shutters are at each window. Two separate small covered porches serve as separate entrances on the front, indicating this was a duplex. A back entry is in view at one side; there is presumably a matching back entry on the other side of the house. Walkways connect each entryway with the sidewalk and street. Shrubs and trees surround the building. This house was built by the Draper Corporation for its employees. Tenements in this context simply means employee housing and not the "slum" housing usually thought of in reference to the word tenements. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 2284: Draper Corporation tenements, 127 Jones Road, 1919; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.B2284. September 1919. Image depicts a two-story wood-shingled house with attic and four chimneys. The building is designed for occupancy by two or more families; there are two separate front entrances, each with their own porch. There is a bay window over each porch. Shrubs and flowers have been planted around the house. This house was built by the Draper Corporation for its employees. Tenements in this context simply means employee housing and not the "slum" housing usually thought of in reference to the word tenements. 25.25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 2285: Draper Corporation tenement, Oak & Freedom streets, 1919; black and white photograph (Box 12, Folder 2)